[Music]
[Applause]
so i work with tons of bikini
competitors and most of them are doing
it wrong when it comes to off-season
before i delve into this i just want to
mention i'm really proud of this all
five of my glute squad members who
competed in wbff this year as amateurs
won their pro card on their very first
show and i'd like to think that the
reason why that happened is because we
train so hard we train harder than the
competition
[Music]
a lot of these competitors don't really
know what they're doing when it comes to
year-round training so i don't even like
the term off-season if you're a
bodybuilder you're always on and yes if
you're a bikini competitor you're a
bodybuilder you're always on it's
year-round you know bodybuilding is
year-round contest prep is year-round i
don't like this whole
mindset like oh it's contest prep i need
to get serious you should be training
hard year round the process of laying
down muscle tissue you know stimulating
growth is very hard it's very hard to
change your physique you don't have time
to waste so yes contest prep is year
round bodybuilding is year round don't
think of it like oh i only got to be on
for these 12 weeks or these 16 weeks and
the rest of the year i can screw off no
it doesn't work that way during your off
season you need to be gaining strength
if you go step on stage and you're the
same strength as you were the year
before why would you look any different
you know off season is called
improvement season well why would you
improve on stage if you didn't improve
your strength during the off season so
here's what i recommend all right you
just finish up a show you're starving
you're tired you're exhausted have a
couple of days where you eat more now i
don't want you gaining 15 pounds over
the next you know a few days but
definitely up your calories indulge in
some treats and then that week that
first week after your show don't go
heavy don't do a lot of compound lifts
stick mostly to bodybuilding circuits
and single joint stuff and high reps
just go to the gym get a decent pump
don't go to failure give yourself a week
of kind of deloading and to put some
weight back on and then the next week
bam you're right back at it you increase
your calories and with the increased
calories strength goes up but don't
overdo it on calories i recommend that
my competitors only gain around 10
percent of body weight during the
off-season above their stage weight so
for example 130-pound competitor would
only gain 13 pounds during the off
season they wouldn't gain 30 pounds they
don't need to gain 20 pounds you gain
too much fat it's hard to lose more
calories does not equal more results
with regards to muscle building right so
you need to chase strength goals for
example with my wbff girls they need
quads you know i love that organization
because you can squat you can lunge you
can have quads whereas nbc and ifbb you
can't have as big a quads so i like to
tell my girls i want you squatting 225
for 10 reps below parallel now it
depends on what they weigh but that's a
really tough goal a couple of my clients
have started that they got three reps i
want them getting 10 reps in about two
months i give them hip thrust goals i
give them squat goals you know i give
them targets on all the big lifts and i
want them getting stronger i want their
absolute strength going up now your
calories will go up your protein can
stay the same or it can even go down a
little bit during off season contrary to
what most people think you know when
you're eating more calories you don't
quite need as much protein as you do
during your prep phase or while you're
cutting when you're cutting protein goes
up a little bit but make no mistake
about it you train hard year-round you
train hard as year-round
and the training doesn't change much
what builds muscle best in a surplus
maintains muscle best in a deficit i'm
going to say that again the methods that
cause you to build muscle best while
you're eating a lot are the same methods
that are going to cause you to retain
muscle best when you're dieting down and
cutting your calories many of my
competitors they do it wrong and that's
what prompted me to make this video i
don't like this mindset of oh
it's prep mode i'm serious now i'm
getting serious because now i'm in prep
mode and the whole rest of the year they
screw up that's not enough time to see
improvements say you compete once or
twice a year and you're only serious for
those 12 weeks or 16 weeks you know what
about the other weeks of the year
training them is fun when they do it
this way because they're kind of
d-trained when they come to me they will
build a lot of strength during their
prep like some of my competitors will
set all-time pr's during peak week like
the monday before their show they're
setting a squat pr or a hip thrust pr
well if you do things right that
shouldn't happen your absolute strength
should peak right before you start
cutting at the end of your off season is
when you should be the strongest the
absolute strongest on all your lifts
meaning you should be squatting the most
weight you've ever squatted hip
thrusting benching military pressing
pull downs all these lists should be at
their all-time peak right before you
start cutting now your relative strength
should peak right before you step on
stage so like the week before peak week
that's when you should hit an all-time
high on relative strength meaning your
strength divided by body weight now what
about cardio you don't want to do too
much cardio during the off-season you
want to save that for when you're trying
to lose fat you want to build a base
during off season that's easy to
maintain and it's easy to ramp up from
if you're doing two a days you know two
strength training sessions a day six
days a week and an hour of cardio each
day you're training three hours a day
during the off season then what the hell
are you gonna do as you start prepping
you have no place to go you're already
up here you're already at your ceiling
you want your baseline to be down here
you know four to five hour and a half
long workouts per week and minimal
cardio for some people no cardio for
others maybe three thirty minute
sessions a week but you don't have to be
doing an hour a day of cardio during
your off season you know an hour of
cardio might burn 300 calories you could
address that by just not eating quite as
much you want to save the cardio for
when it gets really hard to lose fat and
it's not even for the calories that it
burns it's more for staving off your
hunger it's more for like distracting
you so you don't eat and maybe causing
you to not eat quite as much because of
that interaction effect it has with your
appetite hormone so cardio is like this
during the off season then it goes like
this during prep and again most of your
pr should be the month before you start
to prep your your personal records your
all-time absolute personal records the
most weight you've ever lifted the only
prs that you might set during peak week
should be body weight exercises you know
because you're at a really low body
weight you might actually hit your first
body weight nordic ham curl where you
come all the way down and come all the
way up during peak week or you might set
a rep record with chin ups you know
maybe you get 12 chin ups for the first
time during peak week because you're so
lean you're so light but your squat your
hip thrust you know your military press
will necessarily go down during prep
because you're losing weight you're
going to lose a little bit of muscle
usually you don't keep all of your
muscle if you lose 15 pounds ideally all
15 pounds would be fat but in the real
world you tend to lose you know 12
pounds of fat and three pounds of muscle
you also just don't have as much energy
to train hard and your hormones are not
optimal because you're depleted you're
dieted down as far as diet right after
the show is concerned you can reverse
diet that's totally fine i like reverse
dieting for many people or you could
just go right back to maintenance either
one works people assume that you have to
reverse diet no you don't you could just
go right back to maintenance the problem
is some people have a hard time keeping
it at maintenance so they do better when
you reverse diet out of the show and
gradually increase calories the times
where you really want to go right back
to maintenance though is if you're
really low in body fat you know if
you're a female and you're 12 body fat
then i would suggest going right back to
maintenance you don't need to build
slowly out of your competition but the
main thing is you gotta train hard
year-round after your show take a week
to deload have some fun in the gym maybe
only go to the gym three times get your
energy back get your mindset right and
the very next week it's building season
you are building muscle and to build
muscle you got to gain strength now for
some competitors especially with you
know ifbb with the pros you can't gain a
lot of muscle in your upper body you
might not be able to train your quads
you can't do squats or lunges because
you don't want your quads getting too
big but that applies to the very elite
the ninety percent of competitors who
need to build muscle to get up to elite
status should not be following the exact
same methods as the people who are
already at the top those people at the
top hammered away at their squats they
hammered away at military place they got
strong at some point and now they've
earned the right to not train those
muscles hard enough and you do need to
train the whole body you need to get
lean how are you going to get lean if
you're only training legs half of your
body you got to train the whole body get
strong build your resting metabolic rate
up where you have a lot of muscle you
have a lot of energy you want your
calories to be up here when you start
prep so you have a big margin to drop
off season you're eating 1400 calories
and doing an hour of cardio a day where
do you start during prep you have
nowhere to go so i want to conclude by
saying just look at what the
bodybuilders used to do you know they'd
gain a lot of weight during the off
season but it'd be a lot of muscle most
of them wouldn't gain too much fat
they'd put on a lot of size but they'd
be strong as hell then they'd cut down
now the bikini competitors don't need to
follow those same methods as the men
because they're different standards and
different body parts that need to be
muscular for example bodybuilders don't
train their glutes much whereas bikini
competitors that's the main thing they
need to train is glutes but you get the
point bodybuilding is year round and
contest prep starts the week after your
show i hope that helps all right that's
a wrap thank you very much for watching
if you like this video make sure you hit
a like make sure you give it a thumbs up
make sure you're subscribed to my
channel i'm going to try to be
consistent from here on out i've taken a
little break but i'm back for now and if
you have any ideas for future videos let
me know in the comments section
great for this
if you like what you saw in this video
and you want to train under my system
and principles then i invite you to
click on the link below and subscribe to
booty by brett and join the thousands of
other happy members who are seeing
amazing results
yes
[Music]